welcome to the stola the stoah is a
digital campfire where we go here and
dialogue about what matters most at the
night's edge what's happening now
[Music]
all right check-ins so I'm doing
check-ins at the beginning of these just
to kind of ground myself in authenticity
so right now I'm feeling really plugged
in the moment feeling really calm but
then there's just like a little uh
bubbling up of anxiety maybe five ten
percent anxiousness was just kind of
drop to seven so today we have Zack
Stein he's he's back at the stoah and
Zack is going to give kind of share his
thoughts on meta politics and then we're
gonna open it up to Q&A and how that is
how the Q&A is gonna look like if you
have a question for Zack just write in
the chat box and I will unmute you and
you can just ask your question there
Zack or if you want me to read your
question on your behalf I will I will do
so and I will be warming does that come
with a few questions so that being said
I'll hand it over to Zack and to share
your thoughts on meta politics thank you
Peter
and it's actually great to be back I
like this because there's so many of you
it's like it's like a classroom it's
much more engaging than one-on-one yes
I'll share a few thoughts I mean before
I get in I do just want to take a moment
to just recognize the continuing
difficulty of the overall situation and
the suffering the pain and especially
the invisible or the unseen or all the
stories that aren't being shared that we
don't know that don't show up on the
news feeds so there's so much of that
right now
excuse me probably a lot of that event
in the background of everyone's
consciousness that everyone knows
someone who is in pain right now and so
just in that you just can't jump into
the business as usual give your talk
kind of thing
context we just wanted to take a moment
to just presence all that in the
background and to kind of clarify what
I'm trying to do which is to say some
things into that to help us grapple with
that and to move through it as I said
last time to find a way to create
cultural resources that could allow us
to become post tragic in our
relationship to this so yeah so that is
said the thing I want to speak about is
a set of ideas that came to me last year
which basically were the result of me
getting so disgusted with political
discourse in the United States and
particularly on social media that I
wanted to find a way to be a
conscientious objector from the culture
wars and it occurred to me that the
things that I was most concerned about
education psychology metaphysics and
some of the things that I was tracking
like existential risk and civilizational
collapse and measurement specifically
measurement as an aspect of a planetary
computational stack I'm gonna get to
that and then the Transfiguration of
human nature in the meta modern moment
these three things I always thought
these were had political implications
but of course I couldn't actually speak
to them within the context of the
culture war without being co-opted by a
particular mimetic tribe specifically
the left-right meta tribes and so I
start thinking well I'm actually
interested in something else and this
term meta politics came to mind and so I
began to research the notion of meta
meta politics and there's some previous
work done which I plug into in mind
blogposts but so if politics is what
counts as politics which is to say you
know elections voting representative
democracy two-party system with
candidates that are paid for
so that's politics Facebook arguing with
your friends on Facebook about
presidential campaigns that's politics
this is what I'm talking about politics
there's other definitions like if you're
at work and there's competition for a
spot and you're in political competition
with your colleague so that's another
kind of politics if I'm talking about
politics capital P American politics
like do you hate Trump or not is it
politics politics as usual right that
those forms of modern politics
specifically the left-right division
they're being transected by meta
political vectors that are beginning to
obsolete them and so these are the
things that I was detecting which made
me so frustrated with contemporary
political discourse as many of us are
because it's actually not capacitive
can't deal with reality and in some ways
it's almost designed to be a simulation
that runs interference between you and
reality so when reality starts to
actually interface again with the
political structure the political
structure itself gets put in brackets
this has already been happening with
things like global warming right or
climate change right so there's a hyper
object this is the point of the best
ways into meta politics is to think
about the notion of a hyper object you
guys know Timothy Morton's term the
hyper object it's very interesting and
but you know politics is great when
you're dealing with regular old objects
things that could be predicted things
that can be measured and understood the
way populations used to be before social
media for example but as soon as you get
the digital
of a planetary financial and cultural
meta system you get a hyper object of
the capitalist world system so
complicated can't be understood
you also get scientific hyper objects
like climate change again so big such a
massively distributed complex process
that we can't be understood now so the
hyper object is the thing that makes
politics be like oh we actually need to
find a new way to make decisions and
choices because our cognitive
apparatuses are being humiliated by the
hyper objects and I don't confuse a
hyper object with something that's not a
hyper object so for example pre-modern
man right encountered nature all right
overwhelmingly complex beyond their
perception and many ways ineffable not a
hyper object I projects very specific
hyper object requires the exhaustion of
scientific apparatus the hyper object is
the conclusion of the best scientific
attempts and actually where science
leads us up and out of what's
comprehensible and into the massively
complex processes like totalize
planetary ecological change right which
is occurring on time cycles at our
centuries-long
and kind of data points that are
innumerable and increasingly complex so
the hyper object of climate change is
one of the things that a lot extinction
rebellion and others are getting people
to beg whoa politics is in brackets
right now politics the way we think it
could work to solve a problem of
engaging a hyper object politics doesn't
work that way we need to actually
rethink at a foundational level
what it means to do politics right and
what's interesting is you can reduce the
actually met a political to the
political and then you get the
politicization of climate science right
you're trying to fit something that's
actually not capture ABBA within the
conceptual framework of politics as
usual you're trying to make it fit right
and so you start to opportunist and
politicize climate science verbs anymore
so you can see there's many there's many
horizons of Piper objects that are kind
of looming over the political space and
making us quite nervous and of course
the pandemic is the hyper object now a
virus is not necessarily a hyper object
right in a controlled environment with
the right things we can come to
basically understand with scientific
apparatuses the nature of viruses now we
can't predict their mutations which will
always be complex for biology and
immunology and specifically vaccines we
can predict the mutations but we can
know that it's going to mutate we can
know the rate of the mutation another
rate of contagion so the virus is not a
hyper object but the pandemic is either
object it's got massively massively
complex set of interrelated moving
pieces and so just like climate change
or you know the total kind of planetary
economic system cultural systems I
described it the sublime overwhelming
complexity of the totalized capitalist
world system beyond comprehension then
you throw something else in which is a
pandemic which ends up being itself
I have project all of these things are
exhausting the capability of politics as
usual
and this is why it's so scary if
I can speak that way so the fears we
have of authoritarian clamped down those
come from our awareness that we're
dealing with hyper object and that we're
in the meta political right that there
would be attempts to suspend politics as
usual
right that's what we know we're in a
grappling with the meta political so
what this means is that all the attempts
to discuss this in terms of the
categories of politics as usual mean
you've been captured that your minds
been captured probably by social media
all right so you're you're missing the
point
if you're distracted by the left-right
division here and you're missing the
point
if you're in the blame game and media
spectacle of politics as usual and so
Facebook has become politics as usual
just worth noting the targeted political
advertisements micro-targeted political
advertisements are part and parcel now
of the process of political campaigning
and voting and so it also means that the
degree to which you are swayed
emotionally and swayed an opinion
formation by the dynamics of your
engagement with Facebook's in terms of
politics as usual also means you're
captured right we can't see clearly the
hyper object looming over all of our
lives infiltrating like right down to
the everyday details of our lives this
hyper object gets in there as they all
do as climate change does as the
political economy of coal planet does
right the hyper objects haunt us and are
moving us out of the political and into
the meta political and eventually to
redefine the political politics as usual
lines of being yesterday's and we can't
use those categories to handle this
problem just like we can't use those
categories to handle existential risk
and civilization of collapse and we
can't use those problems to handle the
measurement meta structure that
characterizes the totalized planetary
computational stack I'll get to that and
we can't use them to handle the dynamics
of human nature itself which is changing
at the biological and technological
level those are the three aspects that I
laid out in my blog posts that had me
moving into the mind of political and
now the pandemic has us all moving into
the bottom political and asking
foundational questions about what it
means to cooperate why we cooperate what
are the best ways to distribute the
shared fruits of our social
collaboration right what are the
responsibilities of personhood what are
the responsibilities of a government how
is collective choice making carried out
under the conditions were in we're again
dressing these foundational questions
and worrying about what's gonna happen
in November when we're supposed to go
stand in line in very crowded buildings
and vote but we actually we all need to
be coming together and actually working
on a design problem the entire
population is working on a design
problem which is the problem with the
future but instead we're going to take a
multiple-choice test and vote for a
couple futures that have been laid out
for us by people who've never actually
talked to us about it so yeah so that's
the kind of intro where you look at the
way the meta political becomes salient
because of the hyper objects which are
kind of these are the things that are in
some ways characteristic of the meta
modern historical epic which is a brief
epic which we are in
but which will end as we usher in a new
world so this is the time between worlds
is the meta modern if I can is when we
first get a sense of the fact that
science brings us up and into its own
exhaustion in confer in confrontation
with diaper objects and that means whoa
go down this is what we can't do
politics if science doesn't give us what
we need how does politics work right the
whole modern emergence that from the
Renaissance to the Enlightenment into
modernity and you give this complex of
science and politics and the removal of
church and state in this whole thing
required that we didn't end up at the
end of the day with these high projects
so all right so that's the first move
and then the second one gets us into
these aspects that we're already in the
atmosphere around us that were already
met at political right so the first one
we can all get which is existential risk
and civilizational collapse and this is
kind of my collaborations with dr.
Bergeron and Hall we're in this vein
which is that this is actually
unprecedented like modern politics
wasn't actually designed to handle
planetary right modern national politics
weren't designed to handle planetary
scale problems of civilizational
collapsed dynamics and potential
existential risk and again this is what
makes us nervous about things like ego
fascism right that okay there's
something that is so big and complex
that surrounds our political systems
that if the environment got crazy enough
you could see how we would just suspend
politics as usual and do something quite
bad at the name of environmental
protection ISM right so that sense that
uh-oh a planetary scale wide risk can't
be handled by national politics as usual
so we're already kind of aware of that
so and similarly with the pandemic right
it used to be that plagues were not
existential risks right because they
were geospatially they were isolated
right even the plagues in Europe it was
like it got bad and it came over from
giant stuff but like the Native
Americans were not aware that there were
the plague in Europe took a long time
for those germs to cross over but we're
in a situation now is becoming
abundantly clear with the complexity of
the travel infrastructures and the
amount of travel happening that the
total enclosure of the civilization on
the planet is basically complete so that
a pandemic is Planetary from square one
and so you know so that's it's worth
noting that's not something that can be
handled by politics as usual it actually
requires a radical international
collaboration and similarly you know
pandemics in the past feel like alike
during the 30 Years War for example in
Europe always brought along with it
economic political turmoil violence war
depression the cetera the equivalent in
medieval terms and but again localized
like a 30 Years War it was in Europe it
didn't and it was in a sense of world
war but it didn't implicate all the
continents in the way that the world
wars we know did so similarly here
you're looking at the second third order
fourth order effects of the pandemic
being Planet Harry in there
and the ripples that spread out and so
we've always known that these issues
that I'm discussing the civilization of
collapse dynamics and planetary risk
scenarios kind of obsolete politics as
usual pandemic is reminding us of that
another thing I discuss in my medical
meta political blog posts is the notion
of a planetary scale measurement
a structure that is wedded to a
computational stack that's also of
planetary scope and so what this means
is basically we're about to measure
everything and basically track it all
and where are we trying to do that
so the Internet of Things is very
popular phrase and it basically is this
way of characterizing the massively
complex sensor network and tracking
devices that would allow us to basically
long the entire economy and halt
economic transactions including
shipments and things in a computer risk
the simple way to say it's actually a
massively distributed computational
stack has talked about by Benjamin
Bratton but what most people are kind of
missing here is that the sharp end of
the stick when it comes to that
planetary computational stack is
actually the measurement infrastructures
that are nestled right up next to us and
that includes like your facebook
psychometric profile back-end that feeds
you the micro-targeted advertisements
and it's going to include the contact
contact tracing networks and it's going
to include the biomedical
infrastructures specifically the
biometric infrastructures that are
rolling out in the wake of the pandemic
so it's always been the ground work the
ground works always kind of been there
but the whole population is now becoming
aware that there's this possibility that
we're all going to be hyper measured I
per tracked and logged in forever
the kind of vast memory store of the
planetary computational stack and so
that is one of these other things that
we worry about and we're starting to
hear it now
with in the context of the pandemic is
the totalized surveillance apparatus
that is basically ready to go already
been used by large swathes of capitalism
again mostly to sell you things but soon
to be used by nation states and so so
this is important that the measurement
structures put in place to handle with
the pandemic are going to be very
complex they already are and medical
measurement is now being put in a
spotlight and it's interesting to see
because I've been studying measurement
and measurement infrastructures for
about 10 years now starting with
standardized testing in schools but
looking across a bunch of fields and
medical testing has been a mess for a
very long time before the pandemics
shined a spotlight on it which is to say
like anyone who gets a virus of any kind
has an individualized reaction to it
right anyone who takes a medical tests
of any time has an individualized
reaction to it rates of medical
measurement error are largely
undocumented but the points within
medical measurement systems for which
error could occur are so numerous that
we know there's high medical measurement
error in normal contexts right so
measurement itself ends up being one of
these kind of like niceties they're like
a thorn in the political which which is
a which is an allusion to the meta
political which is to say the
measurements are supposedly where the
social system contacts reality right the
measurement is where the social system
contacts reality but what about the
measurement error and we're going to be
thinking about that in a very detailed
way and anyone who studies metrology
which is the fields concerned with
making and testing measurement
instruments you know that measurement
error is part of measurement just is
and if you're if you're building
instrument you can actually study how
the error works which is to say you can
come to be knowing something about where
and why errors occur with your
measurement instrument Charles Sanders
purse what am i heroes some of you will
know him I'm not gonna get into it he
was in metrologist so some of this I got
from him and then working with Pheo
Dawson it was a psychometrician electic
ax come to learn about it oh yeah
whenever you're using a measurement
instrument so important to also have
part of the discourse about it be about
the nature of its errors right the error
bars confidence intervals around the
point and so where's the discussion of
that it might have been medical
measurement pre-pandemic you go to a
functional medicine doctor they're gonna
take like ten thousand dollars worth of
tests and do you ever have a discussion
about the forms of measurement error the
company of those tests right no is the
answer and if you're in a normal medical
context not a fancy functional medicine
context just a normal medical context
when you're discussing medical errors
with doctors right Lyme's disease tests
cost thousands of dollars medical
measurement errors BIC witness so false
positives false negatives in Diagnostics
we're already an issue in medical
testing now we're going to look at it
but we're also wetting those medical
diagnostics for the first time two
socio-political structures right which
means that there's a political content
now engaged with that medical
measurement error question before is
just about am i sick and what do I have
now it's about can I travel by free of
quarantine right am i a stigmatized
citizen right so we're running this very
delicate line up and into a biometric
infrastructure that's political and
moved up and into a larger surveillance
apparatus of the totalize planetary
computational stack
so as the hats and then the final vector
which I mentioned and in the blog post
in is also relevant here is the nature
of personhood and the transformations of
personhood that are accompanying us
through this time between worlds and
just like the modern politics as usual
can't handle this the modern identity
structure also can't handle this
the modern self right which is different
from the medieval self let's say which
is different from the like ancient
itself or archaic self I'm not going to
go into the whole theories of cultural
evolution and how these things are
encased within each identity structure
or uniquely but the modern self was the
thing that was distinct you are
autonomous
you were a citizen you voted and you
used reason and then eventually you
became this self-interested rational
economic actor of fiction but these
assumptions of personhood which
characterized the amount of emotion are
also breaking down and the kind of
viscous solution of the kind of meta
modern cultural landscape a kind of
white noise of over saturation and kind
of semiotic hyper confusion has
dissolved slowly dissolved the core of
the sovereign modern self so what this
means is that we are in a schizophrenic
or psychotic moment that's a culture
where we don't know what it means to be
a person anymore and that is meta
political because what it means is that
it will it all comes down the whole
political structure all the modernity a
political structure comes down to the
individual
right specifically the blank-slate
individual as Patrick Ryan talked about
here on the Stokes the other day and so
you're looking at but and postmodernity
was signaling this but they had no way
of actually embodying it because they
were academics working in modern
academic institutions making a lot of
money for taking modernity as a writer
so they were a modern self talking about
the end of the modern self the modern
self had actually ended we are now in
the confusion of trying to become a new
kind of person a new kind of human and
and so that means that a lot of us look
at the modern political structure and
thankfulness doesn't make sense this
might have made sense in the 1950s or
the 1970s when there was a certain kind
of cohesion to the modern person the
modern family the modern kind of a life
trajectory through these phases etc but
now so you wonder why the youth don't
vote no it's because they know this
system wasn't designed for them it was
designed for their grandparents
basically so so that's the final meta
political bit which was also brought to
a head with a pandemic which is that as
we reflect on the suffering and death
and as we reflect on the economic
precarity and the complete intertwine
'men of all the people on the planet in
this event right we wonder what it means
to be an isolated abstract individual
like how can that be like I did nothing
I didn't choose any of this it's all
happening to me and yet also my
individual choice to go out or not go
out somehow could have through X in an
exponential like spreading like I could
cause thousands of people to die just by
making the wrong choice
so there's this weird breakdown in
intertwine meds and kind of like you
know wiping away in the sand like the
mandala of the modern self just like
blowing the sand mandala of the modern
self like off the thing and and so here
we are figuring out what to do with
politics as usual which is gonna stick
around and they still have the guns and
they still have the money and Jim
Morrison would say you know but we have
the numbers and are actually living in
reality whereas they're working
basically to try to create simulations
of it that will be useful to control us
so it's interesting to consider what
does many political practice look like
in the context of politics as usual and
the opportunity now with as I mentioned
last time the time between worlds ness
and battle and heaven which is part of
this new personhood story meta political
practice ends up being right at home
right right with your speech and how you
spend your time and specifically how you
engage or do not engage with politics as
usual so yeah so there's something about
the when the meta political Dawn's and
everyone starts to see that we have
bracketing politics as usual
it's a risky moment because one things
politics does is it sublimates open
conflict it's like we're not gonna
actually fight we're gonna do this thing
called politics but when politics is in
brackets and you know that well the
given political structure actually hands
on this problem then you kind of take
the gloves off right and you're trying
to get down to brass tacks --is and
actually change something fix something
so there's a delicacy here which means
that politics will actually become more
heated and here I'm gonna use the
broader broader term of politics which
means that like collegial politics is
going to become crazy spouse husband
politics enter gender politics like all
that's going to become really intense
and with the possibility to totally
change which is to say that we're gonna
have to get real with one another and
actually start bracketing politics in
those contexts too and getting to the
real eyes to the reality of what we're
both for where we are all together
confronting so yeah the meta political
is usually an invitation to change the
nature of conversation to talk about
something that's real instead of
remaining in the simulation of politics
as usual and that works in all these
levels from like the husband wife
through the like worked relationship up
into politics as we know it so yeah so
expect to actually in context where
normally you'd be politicking expect to
be able to put that aside and actually
have a conversation maybe for the first
time in a while and that's meta
political practice so I'll leave it at
that and take some questions so if you
have any questions just write in the
chat box and I told me to read on your
behalf you're saying to keep that now
I'll warm up Zach with a question okay
there's so much like juiciness I could
geek out with you on this all day so
there's two questions that feel alive to
me and I don't know which one to go with
one is about mimetic mediation and this
term psychodynamic is political or the
psychodynamic is political and the other
questions about Richard Spencer so which
one which what do you think feels most
alive there have no idea
legal crowdsource it
okay so Richard Spencer you started that
article the first one of the meta
politics mentioning that you discovered
that term from Richard Spencer if I
recall I think he got it from the
dissident right in in the European
movement that dissident right your P
movement and I was thinking while you
were talking it's like no he is so and I
think he is earnest in in his belief on
white nationalism but he's so outside
Overton Window with that it's like he
almost had to get creative and go met a
political in a way so I'm curious
and this might gets like inside baseball
with the culture war stuff but I'm
curious how you think the dissident
right role played in kind of putting
this you know question at the forefront
yes I mean that is where I first kind of
determine in the lips of the white
nationalist who was also what you call
ago a race survivalist
like ban and right so there was an
awareness after 1972 again that we were
going to be looking at a situation where
nation states we're going to begin to
lose sovereignty and we're gonna have a
lot of very complex ecological and
economic dynamics and some conservatives
said okay let's drop the charade of
modern politics that there's a blank
slate and that everyone is useful and
actually just say what we've been saying
behind closed doors for a long time
among the aristocrats and just say it
openly which is that we're looking at
for those like ourselves when the
hits the fan on a planetary scale and so
this was the meta political vector that
Spencer and banna and others speak into
which is that
yeah we're questioning one of the
foundational assumptions of modern
politics
typically late modern politics and
saying that race is actually relevant in
a different way than you think it is to
do in politics and so and that's why so
many there's so much nervousness around
Trump around Bain and around the new
authoritarianism because in a sense
they're a little bit more aware than the
kind of well behaved left in the blue
church these guys are actually a little
bit more aware that the meta political
moment is ripe and that shit's about to
get real and we need to be prepared for
that and so yes that's one of the
reasons I want to start thinking about
getting more progressive people more
explicitly embracing meta political
practice which is a Rican sieving of
what it means to do politics rather than
a figuring out how to win at what has
counted as politics right and now I
obviously do not support Spencer or
Bannon in any way but I do think that
they have caught they've caught a lot of
people off-guard
right like Trump won because these guys
caught the blue church completely
off-guard there's many other reasons of
course but so it's important to just
think that yeah you know you want to
like put it in the stark terms like the
bad guys are already going about a
political right so we need to figure out
what it would mean for the good guys to
start making meta political practice a
primary objective as opposed to the good
guys trying to win according to the
rules of the old system and if we had
more time I would inquire into the good
guy bad guy terminology but let's go to
the questions and Jacob you had a
question sure thank you
you hear me yeah so I was wondering I'm
not exactly sure what it is that I'm
looking for yeah but I felt like there
was some thing that could be drawn out
when Zach was talking about the blowing
away of the modern self San mandala and
the ideas of the pre tragic and post
tragic and kind of what he talked about
with Andrew Sweeney and in the last
chapter of his book which is awesome oh
yeah feel free to just riff on that but
that's what I feel like it's gonna be
the most interesting yeah
and it's a it's the meta political but
kind of like issue that I work on the
most it's just this question of the
nature of personhood and the the
changing nature of personhood and the
lingering kind of like misidentification
so many of us have with the modern
identity with the modern self that were
often taught in schools and taught by
our parents and others to like be that
modern self that's what it means to be
successful but life conditions are such
that we know that this is not the case
that a new form of personhood has been
emerging specifically since digital
became ubiquitous but was already
emerging before them and you know one
way to think about it is under the
notion that all uses of sovereignty all
right that that the modern self was
autonomous right in the content sense
ideally but the the self that's emerging
if there is to be a future needs to be a
sovereign self which is different and
requires a different political apparatus
to
and utilize it that the sovereign self
is threatening to traditional modern
structures but the sovereign itself is
the very energy that the future
political structures need to figure out
a way to run on right so this is that
distributed intelligence versus like
complicated hierarchical modern machine
intelligence so so that's some of it
sometimes Gaffin and I talk about unique
self Symphony right that's a kind of
homogenized or standardized
differentiated modern self which is like
your a non unique demographic category
with this much weighting in terms of
your how much your vote counts and etc
whereas the system we're looking at ends
up being one that has uniqueness as a
factor which is the best way to do sense
making actually is with a unique unique
vectors of input as opposed to like
standardized vectors of input that's
another conversation so unique nodal
points and then each unique nodal point
comes together with other unique nodal
points and you get what we've called a
unique self Symphony and that's kind of
a term of art but there's other ways to
think about it the mystical body of
Christ the corpus mysticum there's
another way to think about it the
kingdom of ends that the kingdom of
nature becomes the kingdom of ends so if
it's been an idea that's been implicit
in the Western tradition that there's
something beyond the kind of like
isolated abstracted individual and
there's something that actually weaves
everyone together into a into a greater
whole so yeah we're breaking out of of
the prior structures yeah so I think
that was like kind of a strange rambling
answer but it was an open question so I
just kind of took it
Amy you get a question about at loss
have a question about lies I was in one
of your texts I read that you cited
Wilbur's idea that outlaws need that our
laws and I've been thinking a lot about
Wilbur's idea about post conventionality
in response to conventionality or anti
conventionality that we need to start
acting in a way that is more in right
relationship with what is actually going
to keep humans alive and sovereign so I
was wondering what the idea of maybe an
a sovereign or an outlaw that a
political landscape might look like in a
in ten years from now if everything went
the way you would want it to what would
that look like
I mean there's a lot in there the yeah
the distinction can made I believe this
was like in the 80s he made a
distinction between there's the law
abiding people right and there's the
outlaws and he was talking about peridot
matically he's like scientists and other
people within parents of people who
follow the rules and then the people who
break the rules right but other people
who break the rules
he differentiated them you said there's
pre-law law and trans law right so some
people break the rules because they
can't even follow them they don't know
how to follow them they don't respect
them they don't even want rules they
just break the rules because they're
pre-law right other people break the
rules guys right yeah I get your rules
I can do your rules all day and I've
done them for a while but I'm looking
for better rules right
so you break the law in the name of a
higher law and this is actually again
something deep in the Western esoteric
tradition the line of Judah right the
archetype of Judah which is the
archetype of David and the Messiah and
etc
the whole notion there was that new
prophecy is possible that the law of the
Talmud can be followed plus one that you
can break the law in the interests of
establishing higher law this is like
deep in the tradition and so similarly
here is what Wilbur's getting at is
getting at the trans law which is the
righteous outlaw not the renegade outlaw
whose self interestedly breaking the law
in the interest of never law but his own
self-preservation but rather the
postconventional like righteous outlaw
who is attempting to establish a
higher-order law or a better law or more
just form of law and so that's very
important set of distinctions and it can
be applied in any domain so it's like
there are some people who propagate
conspiracy theories and things about the
virus and stuff like that and they're
negating normative laws of thought right
yeah that's just some crazy like
that's you're breaking the law of Reason
when you say these things right and but
they're saying no I'm trans rational
right above reason and you're stuck in
reason and you can't see how this crazy
out there stuff is actually beyond
reason it's mystical it's advanced more
advanced would you have to call that
Bluff right because a lot of this stuff
that is breaking the laws of
conventional reason is actually pre
rational right it's actually your
progression below the norms or reason in
order to protect one's self esteem and
emotional stability and other things
like most people regress under pressure
to pre rational forms of justification
but there are some trans rational ways
of making sense of things and include
categories like a causal right non-local
which are not the result of not
understanding reason in science but the
result of
standing or easing understand the
reasoning in science all day and then
looking at the hyper object I mean like
sorry science you're not a hundred
percent of the starting so we have to
make it clear when we're looking at the
landscape especially these consumers
conspiracy theories coming out of the
mouths of spiritual teacher types you
have to look at this stuff and say is
that pre rational or is that trans
rational right again a beautiful will
barian construct of the pre trans
fallacy right that they're both not
rational but not everything that's not
rational is created equal that there are
things that are irrational plus
admitting to the ineffable rational plus
admitting to the a causal non-local but
a lot of the stuff that I'm saying which
is coming out of models of spiritual
teacher types is pre rational it's
magical thinking
it's infantile cognition for the sake of
basically self-preservation and in-group
out-group queuing which is to say you're
recruiting a cult around you who's
willing to believe the same irrational
stuff that you are and so kind of an
affront to the normies who you feel
superior over so anyway I just said nice
to say that because that's all happening
out there and it's been bothering me
with that conspiracy theory stuff not
that there are not conspiracies and not
that there are not transnational views
of pandemic there are both of those
things but most of the stuff is pre
rational magical thinking to protect our
identities none of that stuff would have
a place in a future like you're asking
for a meaning where we'd have a bunch of
sovereign individuals so what exactly
that looks like like the skin on the
bones of the notion of the unique self
symphony ends up getting into the work
that I did on the thirteen social
miracles in my book so my book I'll I
had these thirteen social miracles which
I described as the condition for the
possibility of an education centric or
humans
Society so that means that basically if
we want to have an economy going and
we're extracting resources from the
earth and we're building a planetary
computational stack why are we doing
that for the infinite accumulation of
abstract fictitious capital that's a
weird reason to do it why don't we do
all that for the sake of humans and
specifically for the sake of the next
generation so the idea was the social
miracles was that we could have the
economy humming and we could build in
bells and whistles that end up routing
the excess energy back into something
like a temple of learning that's perched
atop the entire economic stack and it's
that temple of learning that allows us
to get all the people the skills that
are there to get and then to get them
into the situations in civilization
where they're useful and then you get
the emergence of the unique self
symphony a civilizational wide scale but
only if you have an education and human
potential actualizing and a routing
system right but that's very complex so
you need to put a lot of resources into
that which means you need to figure out
how to disentangle the fictitious
capital that sits atop the actual
productive economy and then cycle the
excess energy back into the human itself
so that the transformation of
consciousness the transformation of
skill and identity and intergenerational
transmission that's the point of the
whole economic socio-political thing
that's why we're doing this and but it
looks like basic income guarantees
rethinking spatial borders actually
redrawing geographical boundaries
between regions that looks like
distributed decentralize health care
system of patient empowerment health
focus it looks like eventual total
planetary demilitarization that looks
like unity between all the world's
religious traditions and trans
scientific dharma alliance
so there's a lot there's 13 of them and
that is all necessary for this new
person to have the kind of a causal
conditions and material realities to
become real just like all the stuff with
modernity that we've come to know and
love and then not like so much all that
stuff allowed the modern person to be
like whoa each get a car we each get a
house wow this is crazy like is this you
know all of that material accoutrements
of the fiction of the modern person
we're gonna need new material
accoutrements to we-we've the imaginal
person of the future what would it be
like to go to school knowing that you're
entering an economy in which wage labor
is not the dominant category that's
weird you're in school for 15 18 years
or something that looks like a school
but it's not training you for a job
because wage labor is not the dominant
category there's a basic income and
there's other ways where people are
making themselves useful and it's this
complex thing that doesn't look like
what we know of as like a job market
right because you enter it voluntarily
right so that's an example or different
material accouterments allow for
different identity like a different
identity construction different identity
possibility so that's just an example
similarly if you were growing up and you
knew that the borders between countries
were different than they are now
like before World War one you should
just go anywhere you wanted if you don't
realize this like passports and stuff
like no you just cruising around I mean
there were some boarders that were
harder to get over the others but there
wasn't this incredibly complex
infrastructure of border security etc
so the question of to what extent you
form your identity based on the idea
that you know there are borders that you
could never get across right what would
it look like if you formed her identity
knowing that there were no borders she
couldn't cross right
so again concrete utopian theorizing is
what it is but that's we need that kind
of social imaginal to think through
what's possible for the identity so yeah
thank you and good questions so we have
about five minutes left do you think we
can sneak in one more question hmm
if we go over just a little bit you know
people can exit whenever they like
Maggie you had a good question if you
can go on off mute NASA to Zack hi this
is really similar to a question above so
I don't want to I want to maybe merge it
since we have one last question um a
couple people in the comment section was
curious about I guess collective choice
making and cooperative sense making and
I was really struck by your introduction
of the hyper object kind of concept and
especially your emphasis that we need to
be aware of the limits of our
instruments and not be captured by what
Peter would probably call my medic
tribal silos so I was curious if you had
any practical suggestions or actionable
ways that you think people could come
together in this time to understand this
pandemic hyper object and sense towards
how we should respond let's see
I mean the the number one thing I think
is being able to ask good questions
about your immediate situation with
other people who are in similar
situation so it's like you could ask
good super abstract questions about
things that could never be confirmed
right and sometimes we think this is
sense-making but this is actually not
sense-making maybe eventually and for
some people it is depending on their
location but for the vast majority of
people since making is how do I ask good
questions about the situation's I'm
actually concretely in and so that would
mean sitting together with people in
your community or in your house and
literally just creating questions
together and so this is something I
picked up in my work with Forrest Landry
I've been working with him for a couple
years now along with some others
building out collective sense making
apparatuses and research and other
things and and one of the key things
that of all of our research is questions
matter so much more than our suppose it
answers to that the majority of the
sense-making struggle is actually
finding the right question or sets of
questions so the creation of what I call
question taxonomy which are brainstorms
groups come together and they brainstorm
questions and again the goal is not to
answer these questions in that meeting
the goal is to come up with questions
and the best most precise deepest
questions together and then you organize
these questions into this taxonomy of
questions and then you look at it
together and you say this is the stuff
that we don't know and the key thing
with asking questions is to move beyond
the questions that are rhetorical
questions right
there were questions they're questions
that it's really a statement but it's
like this guy says the question you know
so you want to get to the real sincere
questions about your immediate situation
that you don't quite know the answer to
or you don't know where to answer at all
but you you need an answer / want an
answer and then you can start moving
into how would I find the answers to
these questions and moving into the next
phase of the process but before you
start trying to like get a definitive
set of propositions that tell you the
state of affairs you need to ask well
what what do i what am I even looking
for alright what would be the
information that would be most help me
given where I'm at Who I am
etc so that's the kind of first tip is
actually keep it simple and focus on
asking good questions together and then
from there a lot will a lot will come
and you know the epistemic humility is
what should be dawning after the
humiliation by the cognitive function of
the object which is to say the right
response does not throw up your hands
and shrug and you can't understand it
because it's hyper object and it's not
the right response it's continuing to
move but with a different frame one
that's got what I call epistemic
humility um which means basically like
knowing that you can't know it all right
and actually knowing that you're always
acting in a certain amount of
uncertainty and this is important
ethically to know like if to hold
yourself generally in these complex
situations because you are making
decisions without full knowledge in
context that often require almost heroic
like kind of forms of trade-offs
so yeah the hyper object is also a
reminder that you're not the hero
all right like it's a deflating again of
the modern ego right the modern egos a
hero figure it out put a period on the
end of that question triumph came nature
win the game right like no that's
obviously not worked out well so we're
in a situation now where the hyper
object is actually forcing us into a
different archetypal way of grappling
out of the simplistic heroic narrative
and into one that is again I think post
tragic something redemptive and
something more about love than about
conquest so I'll end it there yeah very
cool there is just one question someone
just asked and I really encourage you to
feel free to swat it away but I'll say
it anyways
Ken's a confirm if he doubles as a lead
guitarist in System of a Down
I do not I'm a bass I'm a bass player
well good that got resolved
cool so R at the hour mark Zack thanks
so much again for coming on the stoah
greatly appreciated I'll post this on
the YouTube channel so everyone can
watch it upcoming events I'll just
mention one a game about living boldly
in a crisis with Joe Edelman that's
coming up at 2 p.m. Eastern Time
definitely check that out and tomorrow
we have Samuel bersia
with institutions and situational
awareness the presentation on that in a
cool event with aj bond on the
narcissistic spotlight calling attention
to our collective narcissism and
building a relationship with it that
being said Stowe is based off a gift
economy if you're inspired variety gift
of the stoah which I'm view in the store
is a gift to the world right now for us
to freely use just go to the website the
stove at CAA and check out the gift
economy at the bottom of the page
everyone thanks so much for coming on
today